good morning everybody really excited to
be here um I'm Tre grer I'm gonna talk
today about uh navigating the evolving
lexicon of information retrieval uh this
slide you'll see uh throughout the day
if you want to scan it there's a um uh
an app for the conference um so there's
an AI powered search community that's um
associated with the book uh with the
book coming out we're creating a
community of um hundreds of search and
AI experts um we're also sponsoring the
app for the conference today so if you
want to um be able to follow along with
sessions interact with people feel free
to grab that that'll be uh shown
throughout the course of the day um also
Charlie mentioned that um there are
physical copies of the AOW search book
over there feel free to go uh thumb
through them uh the ebook is not easy to
thumb through it's basically it's
clearly it's impossible to thumb through
um and uh getting to you know look
through it and check and see what's
there is um I got it about a week ago
and was uh super excited uh it should be
coming out in a couple of weeks for
everybody who's ordered a copy and if
you haven't ordered a copy um definitely
uh you can uh so a little bit of
background about me um of course I'm the
author of AI powered search I um have a
search consulting company called search
kernel uh where I uh help companies uh
building iow search also as uh Charlie
mentioned I just um joined as a
technical adviser for open source
connections so if you are clients of
theirs or want to be clients of theirs
you can get access to me through them uh
I'm also U recently started as an
Adjunct professor uh teaching computer
science at my local
University uh today's talk since I get
to do the keynote is um not a uh rah rah
inspirational let's get ready for AI
powered search let's get ready for
relevance talk um I've done those before
but uh with the book coming out um a lot
of people in here are experts in search
um a lot of people are experts in AI um
a lot of people are neither uh and uh
there's uh over the last couple of years
there's this evolving lexicon that I'm
sure you've all um encountered uh for
those who maybe came from the uh
traditional uh sort of like loose scene
based search engines whether it's you
know solar elastic search loose directly
open search um you know there's certain
terminology that may be a little bit
foreign um coming from the more you sort
of AI deep learning World um a lot of
it's been normalized at this point but
uh what I wanted to do today is do a
very quick Breeze through um sort of a a
survey of different topics in AI powered
search um if you've you know seen many
of these before um bear with me and if
you haven't hopefully it can be a sort
of refresher to fill in lots of space
what I've found over time is that as
people start start to work in um machine
learning uh focused on search and in AI
powered search that often they come uh
to search from very particular angle so
maybe they start with Vector databases
and embeddings and their entire focus is
on semantic search for example um it's
really easy to get started there uh but
there's a whole sphere of uh AI powered
search techniques focused on collecting
user behavioral signals for example and
doing things like signals boosting
especially in e-commerce to make sure
that the top results come back to do
things like personalized search and
recommendations uh to do things uh like
uh lexical semantic search as opposed to
Dent Spector based semantic search um
you may have heard terms like uh
multimodal search uh uh late interaction
cross encoders buy encoders and you you
maybe kind of sort of have an idea of
what it is but maybe also you uh like
you have really no idea what the
difference between dense Vector search
that you did five years ago and buy
encoders is now or like what is a cross
encoder and how is it different from a
learning to rank model so what I wanted
to do today is just do a very quick kind
of run through and then hopefully I'll
have some time for questions at the end
we'll see what we can
do uh okay so the book AI powered search
check it out uh no more on
that okay so the first uh term I wanted
to go through um in our vernacular um
and you know all of this is in the book
um so um you you can find it there is
reflected intelligence uh so this this
is you know very simply it's a little
bit of a marketing kind of term but
reflected intelligence is just uh the
idea of feedback loops it's like similar
to reinforcement learning uh users come
in they run searches we they see some
search results they take some action on
those search results and then we collect
those actions and use them to build
models that can then improve future
searches so uh a very um common uh model
for this is uh as an example somebody
searches for iPad we uh record the uh
searches that they ran over here as well
as the documents that they saw and in
what order they then take some action
maybe they click maybe they add to cart
maybe they purchase and then after that
we have some algorithm that does
processing on those signals and
generates a machine learning model that
can be plugged into the production
system to improve uh search going
forward so the uh there there's lots of
different types of reflected
intelligence models up here on the top
left uh there's a signals boosting uh
feedback loop uh that focuses on
boosting the most popular results to the
Top This is a recommendations flow with
collaborative filtering this is a
learning to rank flow that uh takes user
behaviors and generates implicit
judgments leveraging click models to
feed those back in into into a learning
to rank system um you can combine that
with manual judgments but the idea here
is that these systems can learn on their
own from your user behaviors so that the
search engine getss smarter and smarter
so we're going to talk about a few of
those uh today so four different
categories of reflected intelligence one
is signals boosting and by the way I I
tend to take these in a production
system and layer them on top of each
other so I'll explain them here really
quickly and sort of how they uh fit
together uh because often times people
see them and think of them independently
and don't know how to how to put them
together so a signals boosting models
are what I like to call popularized
relevancy so this is the idea of uh
learning exactly what your users want to
see based upon particular queries what
they're actually clicking on and making
sure that the top results show up at the
top your users are literally telling you
the right answer so this is basically
just listening to them uh learning to
rank I refer to is generalized relevancy
this is the idea of uh using user
behaviors to try to and and feature
engineering on your documents to try to
figure out what types of features lead
to higher relev
and so this allows you to build a
generalized ranking model that can be
applied to all your searches um
regardless of whether it's something
people have searched for or not the
third category is uh collaborative
filtering and Matrix factorization uh I
refer to this as personalized relevancy
uh so in this case you're learning about
specific users their traits their
profiles um and you're using this to
generate recommendations for them or to
generate personalized uh relevance uh or
personalized search results based upon
that users um interests um and lastly
there's this uh category of Knowledge
Graph learning from signals so obviously
you can uh learn from your documents uh
you know key terms phrases uh and uh you
know misspellings things like that but
also based upon the queries users type
in the follow on queries they uh type in
and the products or documents they
interact with you can also mine query
logs to be able to generate a semantic
understanding of domain specific
language for the end user so we'll go
through these really quickly so what is
signals
boosting uh this is plain bm25 I've got
some results here um I'm searching for
iPad um as you can see these are very
bad results uh the reason these are bad
results U the name is iPad which is uh
you know fine but notice that the
manufacturer here is also iPad these are
uh bad results this is bad data it's
labeled incorrectly but because this
data is labeled incorrectly and it
happens to put the name of the product
in the manufacturer field instead of
Apple uh these results go straight to
the top uh so obviously this is not the
intent of the user so for a very popular
query we would do we would build a
signals boosting model uh this flow is
exactly the same for all of the uh
reflected intelligence models user runs
the search collects the queries collect
the following actions and then run some
uh uh aggregation or machine learning
model process here to build and so in
this case we're just doing an
aggregation of the uh documents that
users actually purchased clicked and Etc
and what you see over here is we're
generating literal boosts the number of
times that somebody clicked on a
document or purchased the document the
more times that happens for a particular
query that document goes higher in the
results very simple model but for your
head queries for your most popular
results this can get you so much value
by just making sure that the right
results that your users want at the top
are at the top so in this case um a
followon search for iPad would um yield
a query for iPad with these boosts
boosting up the specific documents that
we know are the best documents for um
users in general uh and so um in order
to do this we need to collect signals
I'm not going to spend time on the slide
but um it's really really important if
you're trying to do signal user
behavioral signals based machine
learning models that you're collecting
your signals and that you're collecting
them in the right format and so um I've
got a you know sort of syntax in the
book um open search recently released a
a feature called user Behavior insights
which does something very similar they
Define a schema for how you can collect
signals to make sure you've got all the
data you need for Downstream model
building um so skip through that um the
idea is to aggregate the signals for
Signal boosting uh once you do that you
generate and store uh boosts for
particular documents for particular
queries and then the next time somebody
runs a search for iPad
these are the original results and these
are the new results we've learned from
user Behavior what the best results are
and we just boot boost them to the top
so that's signals boosting uh there's
lots of techniques for improving signals
boosting that's a very basic signals
boosting model uh you know this good to
normalize queries to enhance the signal
um you know by signal spam where
particular users have an undue influence
on the search engine uh combining
multiple signal types uh implementing
time decays and uh index time versus
query time uh signals boosting not going
to talk about this today because I'm
trying to go quickly uh through lots of
material but these are all uh things
that we cover in the book that you can
dive into or you can ask afterwards if
you're curious how this works uh
learning to rank is the next category of
reflected intelligence model signals
based um ranking again the exact same
flow users run searches collect the
query collect the results build a
machine learning model in this case
we're building a ranking classifier so
uh you can see over here that this is a
very simp Le uh machine learning model
it's just got some features that are in
documents and it's learning the weights
of those features uh once those weights
are learned that model gets put into
production and subsequently the next
time somebody searches for something uh
doesn't have to be iPad can be any
search uh that model is used as the
generalized ranking model for all
results coming in uh the way this
happens so you you can manually create
judgments by having somebody annotate
document and relevance ranks for
particular queries you can also use
something called click models so click
models are uh are the ability to take
your users queries uh clicks um and and
other behavior and to learn based upon
those behaviors what the user likely
finds relevant so for example if they
run a search um for iPad and most users
are skipping over the first result
consistently that's probably a signal
that that first result is not the most
relevant
if there's a you know higher proportion
of people clicking on the second and
third results those are probably more
relevant uh click models get way more
complicated than that there's tons of
biases you have to address and avoid um
and uh there's an entire chapter on it
in the book um written by Doug uh
Turnbull so I definitely recommend you
catch it you check it out but again the
idea is signals come in you
automatically can create judgment lists
from that you train the model and then
you create this Loop this feedback loop
of constant improving uh learning to
rank models based upon the implicit
judgments from user behavior from these
click
models if you want to learn more about
learning to rank and click models and
implicit judgments uh you can check out
these three chapters of the book chapter
12 also covers overcoming ranking bias
through Active Learning uh which I'm not
going to talk about
today um so then we get to personalize
relevance things like collaborative
filtering and Matrix
factorization this looks very familiar
by now uh you've got a loop people run
searches people uh click interact and
this case the mo the model that we're
building the the algorithm we're running
is a matrix factorization model uh so
the idea here is that we uh take a user
iter item interaction Matrix we try to
learn a user to feature Matrix and an
item to feature Matrix and then uh based
upon that we're approximating the actual
behaviors we saw from the end users we
can then take that Matrix that we've
learned uh do a matrix multiplication
and then we end up with uh Rec
recommendations generated so that we can
say for a particular user what items
they're likely to prefer based upon
their past behaviors so in this case
I've got Alonzo and for Alonzo I'm
recommending these particular documents
based upon his interactions with other
similar
documents um you know this is the
standard users uh who purchased uh these
products also purchases other products
users who like this also like these
things that you see on Amazon but the
idea is uh to look at the behaviors of
other users not look at the content at
all just look at their behaviors and
based upon other users behaviors who are
similar based upon the items they've
interacted with we uh infer what this
particular user is likely to uh find
relevant and we recommend to them uh so
uh one algorithm I like to use is
alternatively squares to implement this
Matrix factorization um not going to
spend time on code today but the idea is
once you've generated those
recommendations in this case these are
recommendations for a user who
previously searched for apple and
MacBook and previously clicked on iPad 2
um Apple iPad iPad and and a MacBook Air
uh you can see these results on the
right are pretty good recommendations so
these are not based upon a search these
are based upon the user's past behaviors
and now we're these are pure
recommendations that we're showing to
the user the way we're showing them to
the user in this case is we're indexing
them into the search engine and um in a
sidecar collection we're then loading
the products that are recommended for
that user applying some boosts based
upon the um the sort of prominence of
that recommendation for that user and
then uh we're we're literally just
showing the recommendations to the user
so we're using the search engine to
serve the recommendations but no actual
search no no keyword-based search is
happening there's a recommendation based
match but um you know I tend to not like
to think of uh search engine and
recommendation systems as separate
disconnected uh services in reality uh
they're you know search and
recommendations are just along a
spectrum and so if you think about
traditional keyword search uh what you
have is a ma you know the search engine
is a matching engine and what you're
doing is you're taking context and
matching on that context and ranking in
the case of a keyword search the context
is the keywords the user typed in that
is your context and if that's all the
context you have that's all you match on
on the flip side if you look at a
recommendation engine usually the
context that you have is the behavior of
the user maybe their profile you know
things you know about the person uh but
you may not have keywords coming in it's
it's literally just showing them
something based upon their past Behavior
but obviously if recommendations are a
matching engine that matches on context
and ranks results and search is a
and ranks results they're fundamentally
the same thing uh the question so then
the question becomes well can we not
think of them as you know two separate
systems but can we think of personalized
search as all the space in between
search and recommendations and the
answer is yes so if we uh look at this
query so this is a non-personalized
query uh the user comes in they type
tablet I have that this is the same user
as before I have that past Behavior
where they search for a Macbook they
search for an iPad uh but in this case
if I don't use that in my user search as
context then these are results they get
um who thinks that these are good
results for the query
tablet nobody these are these are bad I
got to like no no the these are really
bad results just plain bm25 uh but uh
what if we took this query knowing about
our user and we use what we know about
our user to just nudge the results a
little bit based upon what we think they
would like um so this is an example of a
personalized search so notice that now I
see these tablets at the top um um but
which are you know based upon the
recommendations these aren't pure
recommendations mind you these are
boosts of documents to make them show up
higher in the search results um so if
you notice at the bottom I've got this
document and this document these are
those same bad search results that we
saw a second ago the first and second
one um the set of search results that I
returned to the end user is actually not
no different all I've done is I've
ranked I've reordered the results in the
search results to boost things that I
think might be for that user so the
reason these are at the top is because
they're better matches they've been
boosted from down below but once I
finish with the results that I've
boosted I just end up with my same you
know default search results that I had
before so this is an example of
personalizing
search uh this is the user item
interaction Matrix I referred to earlier
that you start with where you've got
users and the items that they've
interacted with and you know some sort
of score based upon how uh relevant they
find those items for themselves uh the
process of Matrix factorization
uh to generate the recommendations uh
starts with that user item Matrix and
tries to break it into these two
different matrices uh while while doing
collaborative filtering is useful where
I basically multiply these this Matrix
and this Matrix back together to
generate recommendations the
intermediate form of these two uh
matrices here is actually quite useful
as well and so what I've actually done
uh when running the ALS algorithm here
for the Matrix factorization is I've
generated a list of user users mapped to
latent features that describe those
users um and I've also mapped each of
the items to a list of latent features
that describe uh those items um so with
this um I can you you can think of this
as a list of floats um a comma separated
list of floats of some number of
Dimensions um you've probably seen that
before in the context of embeddings for
Content so this is basically a
behavioral embedding this is learning uh
and embedding based upon just user
behavior from the uh user interaction
data um with that data with those
embeddings we can then uh take them and
apply them in various ways we can uh use
them to try to uh you know because we've
uh tagged documents with those uh latent
features that were learned about the
documents we can then match users to
those so instead of just generating
recommendations we can actually use them
for you know Vector search um so in this
case I can do personalization where I
have for example someone searching for
microwave they've previously searched
for Hello Kitty plush toy G electric
razor black GE bright white light bulbs
and Samsung stainless seel refrigerator
um I can use all of those of course and
you know generate some not great results
over here um just because I searched for
a Hello Kitty plush toy recently doesn't
necessarily mean I one Hello Kitty
microwave U so one of the things that we
go through in the book is uh the idea of
creating guard rails around uh different
categories so for example uh the only
one of these that is particularly useful
in this context is the stainless steel
refrigerator because it's in the
category of appliances and if I'm
looking for appliances and I previously
looked for stainless steel that's
probably what I'm looking for not Hello
Kitty because I looked at a plush toy or
maybe my kid looked at a plush toy got
three young girls and that's the kind of
thing that they would do I don't want to
Hello Kitty microwave as a result uh so
um as I mentioned those uh latent
features that are learned in the
interaction Matrix uh are very
comparable uh to the kind of embeddings
that we get uh from uh a Transformer
model uh when we're encoding content
when we're coding text so uh in this
example um yeah these are some this is
fake data so this is overly simplified
uh but the idea here is that uh say I
had a 768 Dimension embedding coming
from some encoder uh model
uh I would you know kind of look at
these and say hey this you know based
upon these particular products this
Dimension and maybe this in combination
with some other dimensions seems to have
some influence on size uh this you know
row here seems to have some influence on
color this feature seems to have some
influence on is this thing kind of like
a computer uh this one seems to
correlate with price in some way um
usually embeddings are are not this
decipherable but obviously Bally
inherently within embeddings we have
encoded uh information about uh
different aspects of of products and
features and and the items that we're
looking at and so uh knowing that these
are all latent features of some sort uh
for items uh and knowing that we can
generate latent features from user
behaviors uh it also means and stands
the reason that we can build multimodal
models not just uh you know text and
images or text and video or text in
audio or text and you know whatever we
can also build them based upon Behavior
so having a um an embedding having a
multimodal model that can both
understand text and behavior and sort of
find the relationships between the two
um is entirely
possible um so you know just as an
example you know text user behaviors and
interactions and images can all be
combined together uh to create a
multimodal model that um can infer not
just from the text but also from user
behaviors what they're looking for so if
you want more about personalization um
chapters four and nine of the book cover
those in pretty good depth uh and the
the last reflected intelligence topic I
want to cover is uh signals based
knowledge graft learning this one's
really quick uh users run queries they
have typos they usually correct the typo
right after um maybe they adjust the
query to um you know type something more
specific type a different color um all
of those user interactions and behaviors
interactions and behaviors can be mined
in order to generate uh taxonomies
knowledge graphs and just overall lists
of related terms misspellings and things
like that so um here's some examples of
you know just discovering related terms
based upon user query Behavior this
these are examples of finding
misspellings where you know poach pad
Maps the touchpad latop Maps the laptop
Etc um if you're building
uh misspelling detection in the search
engine you're going to find much better
results if assuming you have enough
signals uh user behaviors you're going
to find much better results by
leveraging what users actually type in
to get a nice list of what users are
looking for and what they're commonly
misspelling uh versus leveraging the
content that's in your index in most
cases uh there's uh you know you can
leverage the content but this the
context of what users are actually
looking for in typing is is typically
missing when you're just looking at uh
content
uh if you want more knowledge graph
learning check out those chapters by
Doug um or uh me and Doug um so quick
summary of the reflected intelligence
models uh signals boosting popularized
relevance boost the most popular results
to the top Bas one user Behavior
learning to rank automatically uh infer
judgments and then use those to train a
generalized model that can be applied to
all your queries uh collaborative
filtering and Matrix factorization can
be used to generate latent features for
users that can be used to to personalize
results and show recommendations and
Knowledge Graph learning can be used to
learn uh semantics and and domain
specific terminology within um uh the
domain of your search
engine okay so next question is what are
vector databases I assume everyone in
here knows what a vector database is so
I'm going to rephrase this and say what
aren't Vector
databases um so it used to be the case
that you know there were a couple of
vector databases and there were search
engines and search engines kind of sort
of had Vector cap ities but not really
and the vector databases uh had Vector
capabilities but not really search
capabilities and you know we've all seen
over the last year or two or three that
uh every single type of engine is
rapidly rushing to become a vector
database um the reality is Vector search
is not really a um and this is my view
might be controversial probably not um I
I don't really view it as a product in
it of itself I view it as a feature so
in my view search engines have Vector
search capabilities some search engines
are hyper optimized for those Vector
search capabilities and those are the
ones that are typically called the
vector databases they call themselves
Vector databases but uh you know every
every engine is rapidly adding these
capabilities and so the the distinction
between like every time I have to say
your search engine or vector database um
it just like I don't know I'm I'm really
tired I'd rather just be able to say
your search engine and know that there's
just different types of search whether
it's n Vector search electrical search
Etc um but maybe someone from a vector
database company wants to come uh smack
me upside the head after this so we'll
see um all right buy encoders what are
buy encoders and how is this different
from uh just you know dense Vector
search like we've been doing for years
and years so um It's You Know by buy
encoders are uh just you know the idea
of taking queries and uh taking
documents and mapping them to uh the
same Vector space so that you can use
queries to search for documents so
typically with the buy encoder um you
have the ability to to you either have
separate um uh encoders for the query
and Doc and documents that have been
trained together or you have one that's
been trained to be able to handle both
but the idea is simply you're generating
a Bings um you know then you take your
query vectors your document vectors you
do a similarity of some sort you know
doc product you know what whatever and
uh generate some results um so that's
you know the way we do Vector
search um and then the question is uh
what are cross encoders and how do they
differ from learning to rank um
so uh buy encoders over here on the left
this is similar to the last um slide you
just saw um have the idea of uh taking
documents um passing them to the encoder
uh and generating embeddings and then
indexing those embeddings putting them
in your search engine or vector database
um uh once once you've done that at
query time you take your query and you
independently encode it and then you
once you've done that you do your vector
similarity uh to against the all the uh
vectors in the index maybe you're using
some approxim approximate nearest
neighbor technique to uh you know make
it much more efficient but the idea is
that um you can independently encode
both the query and the document um then
you generate your similarity score so in
general this is fairly efficient uh you
know as Vector these two Vector
comparisons go uh a cross encoder is
very different so if you remember
earlier we talked about learning to rank
and the idea behind learning to rank is
that we build a rank and classifier and
the rank and classifier you know uses
judgments and what have you and uh has a
Model A generalizable model that we can
apply to score and rank all results uh a
cross encoder takes documents in and
takes query in but instead of encoding
them separately it encodes them together
and so the idea here is that uh if I
just I'll make up an example um imagine
that I have some documents here for uh
hiking so there's you know hiking in the
snow hiking on the mountain beginning
hiking camping Etc and then I've got a
query for Mountain hike so the query for
Mountain hike if I use a buy encoder is
going to find me things that are like
you know hiking and find me things that
are like mountains and these documents
over here have been encoded based upon
their content with a with a cross
encoder I actually take my each document
and each query and I encode them
together which means I can use the
context the attention from my documents
to influence the interpretation of my
query and I can use the context of my
query to influence the interpretation of
my documents what that means is that if
I type a query for Mountain hike then
the embedding that's generated for all
of the documents is based upon how those
documents are related to Mountain hike
the context of mountain hike is is added
into their embedding so generally
speaking you're going to get much better
relevance uh when you use a cross
encoder than when you use buy encoder
because you're able to look sort of the
documents can look across to the queries
and the queries can look across to the
documents and understand their context
to generate better ranking about how
they're
related uh the downside of cross
encoders is that they're really slow so
uh you can't take you know millions of
documents and run them through a cross a
cross- encoder often you can't even take
thousands um typically you're going to
take maybe the first page or two or you
know depending upon how beef your server
is um you're going to take the top in
results and rerank those with a cross
encoder to try to get the best first or
second or third page uh because this
keep in mind this is encoding every
query and every document pairwise
together which is slow and takes time
and you're you're not going to be able
to wait for the search engine to uh do
all that processing so typically when
you're doing Vector search you would run
a buy encoder as a first phase um you
know realistically you probably have an
approximate nearest neighbor algorithm
that filters down uh efficiently and
then you uh sort of you know grab and
and rerank maybe with the buy encoder to
get the top in you maybe it's in the
thousands um and then uh or maybe in the
hundreds and then you U would pass that
to your cross encoder just to rerank the
top results to get the best uh results
there so that's a cross encoder um next
topic is semantic knowledge
graphs so um these are basically the
concept of leveraging your inverted
index as a graph um so with an inverted
index so with a sparse inverted index um
you uh have the ability to um uh use a
forward index and a inverted index and
with that you can uh you know for
example search for a scale of java um uh
Traverse to the documents that contain
that term um using the inverted index
and then from there from those documents
you can use the forward index to find
other related nodes or terms within your
index and because uh you go to from the
Ford index the inverted index to the
Ford index you can continue traversing
to the inverted index again and the
forward index again allowing you to have
this probabilistic um traversal through
uh your search results um I'm going to
show an example of the output of that in
a second um as we talk about sparse
versus dense vector retrieval and so um
similar to uh well I just say that uh
sparse versus dense Vector retrieval
there's lots of ways to implement this
um you've got your sort of traditional
token matching which is what you would
do with a um El exical search engine
with keywords um then you've got your
pure dense Vector search where you're
just taking embeddings buy encoders you
know cross encoders Etc um and then in
between we've got all sorts of other
techniques that we can use to implement
semantic search and retrieval so um here
we've got term expansion which is just
you know taking a lexical approach and
automatically learning some uh expand
expanded representation that we can run
a search on so Spade is a good example
of this as is as are semantic knowledge
graphs um sparse retrieval and dense
reranking or sort of in the Middle where
we would run uh a sparse retrieval first
and then use vectors to rescore and then
hybrid sparse retrieval with DSE Vector
search is another one this would be
something like um uh reciprocal rank
Fusion you doing a hybrid search here
but there's all these different
techniques I think we often tend to
think of well I've got lexical search
and I've got dense Vector search and
I've got a hybrid search but it's all a
spectrum and there's lots of different
techniques that you can combine based
upon your use case um so as an example
um this is just a sem a sparse lexical
semantic search uh for good kimchi and
Charlotte and I'm not going to get into
the you know nuances of how this is
being parsed and understood and
interpreted but in terms of the
expansion you can see the semantic
Knowledge Graph expansion up here can
identify the type of document is Korean
and related terms to expand or things
like barbecue ribs pork and brisket
whereas Spade uh Plus+ um generates
these sorts of uh tokens that you could
index and then match on they don't look
as good they function okay U but that's
an example of sparse electrical semantic
search happy to talk with uh anybody
more offline about
those um and then Vector quantization
we're going to go quickly through this
but like I said I'm happy to talk more
about this later um there's multiple
different approaches to uh improving the
efficiency of your vector search so
quantization is you know if this
represents a float 32 uh Vector
representing the pixels in this um image
uh this would represent a scalar
quantization meaning taking that float
32 and just using less bits to store um
so I still have most of the information
represented but um using way less memory
and then this last one is an example of
binary quantization where I'm using a
single bit you know is it black or is it
white to represent the image and while I
do lose some information uh by and large
I can still still tell mostly what this
represents so um there's a couple
different types of there's many
different types of quantization a few of
the popular ones are scaler quantization
which is taking uh this the idea of what
I just showed of taking for example a
float mapping it down to an integer um
uh in this case I go from all of the
possible values of a float to you know
256 values that that can be represented
by an 8 integer um if I reduce my
embeddings down to this memory size
because so going from 32 bits to eight
bits um I uh my I I reduced my index
size by 75% while keeping my recall at
you know about 93% at least in the
examples that I was running with the
data I was working with and if you do
reranking on the top results uh based
upon higher Fidelity vectors you can
actually get back to full recall there
um binary quantization is the extreme of
scalar quantization the number of yeah
uh bits I'm using is one and so there's
a couple of different ways to do binary
quantization using a simple threshold a
non-uniform uh binary quantization or a
modelbased binary quantization where the
uh Transformer actually understands how
to Output the best binary quantization
uh which works better than
post-processing um but similar kind of
uh thing here I reduced my index size by
almost 97% while keeping 60% recall and
in my data at least I was able to get
back to you know full recall by
reranking like twice the the number of
results U product quantization is a more
complicated one um this one basically
allows you to control the level of
compression that you're going to be um
using sort of as much as you want so
you're not limited to a single bit you
can actually compress further than
binary quantization and you've got um
sort of all the leverage to do that it's
based upon the concept of uh clustering
your breaking your big Vector into sub
vectors clustering those into a certain
number of uh cluster centroids and then
assigning those and indexing those um
and um and using those as the basis of
search um so uh continue on with that uh
matka um em uh embeddings are very
similar concept so some models like mix
spread for example their models um have
this um have this ability to uh have a
hierarchical embedding so what that
means is that uh the first half of the
embedding contains enough information to
get you high recall and then the second
half of the embedding sort of is is a
fine tuning on those original embeddings
to get you uh more more um uh more
recall so the idea with these is at any
point you can cut the embedding in half
and still get fairly good recall so if I
cut cut it in you know in half here I
still get 70% recall if I cut it in half
again I get 47% recall but with
reranking of the top results I can get
back up close to um perfect recall at
least you know a couple Dimensions down
uh not not for long but it it works
um uh let's see I'm going to skip to
multimodal search um I think everybody
knows what multimotive search is so in
this context we're doing things like uh
search searching on images and text so
if I search for something like superhero
flying I get uh you know these results
if I search for superheroes flying the
encoder knows enough about this to to
know that it's generally
plural I can also do things like let me
search for this DeLorean and find
similar images but I can also do sort of
this this cross uh modality search here
where I've got this image plus the word
superhero and I get this cool car here
with uh Black Panther on top and then
these are all sort of Heroes of their
stories with these cool cars um hybrid
search is similar if I want to be able
to combine embeddings with sort of
lexical search with embeddings um in
this case these results contain some of
the correct results and from lexical
search these Vector results contain some
of the right results and then when I do
a hybrid search this is using an
algorithm called reciprocal rank Fusion
I am able to generate um ranked results
that are um uh you know containing all
the right results
ranked um and then lastly um Foundation
models um there's there's multiple types
of foundation models so what are
Foundation models there's large language
models which we all know and love
there's Vision Foundation models
multimodal Foundation models that
combine multiple different um uh
modalities within uh these and then
audio Foundation models I um am
personally really um excited about
what's coming with lated interaction
models so I think Joe's going to talk
about Co pal so I'm not going to spend
much time on this but um if you look at
the the cert and Colbert V2 models um
the intuition Behind These is that they
go from what we had way back when uh
word Toc first came out in like 2013
where every single word generated its
own embedding um and then once we got
you know Transformers uh they sort of
went away from that and went to encoding
you know larger chunks of text and sort
of you know losing a little bit of the
context of each individual word while
gaining the context of the entire
sentence so um with cobbert V2 cert and
cert V2 we now have the ability to
create multi or I'm going to call it
multivalued um vectors which basically
means you know in a field in the search
engine I can have multiple different uh
vectors and I can do one for each word
so I can take every single word in my
document give it its own Vector but that
Vector is contextualized based upon the
entire document and what's surrounding
it not just that individual word and so
the um the quality of this is like
through the roof relative to other uh
single vectoring uh encoding uh
techniques um I'm not going to spend any
more time on this because we're close on
time and I want you to hear from Joe um
and again he was going to talk about Co
Pali but the these techniques are sort
of The Cutting Edge and what I consider
to be the next Frontier of uh being able
to uh search and so coaly in particular
if you look here this this is almost
like you know this is what's being
searched instead of sort of parsing PDFs
and parsing documents into individual
pieces I am now taking the original PDF
the image passing it to the um the
encoder and having it sort of interpret
and understand the document and if I
type um you know which hour of the day
had the highest overall electricity
generation 2019 it's finding the hot
spots in these patches on this
particular uh document so this ability
to search directly on the documents
without all this intermediate sort of
processing and chunking and OCR and all
these things uh lead to significantly
better results um so last slide um
future search and Foundation model so
I've been building search my entire
career and uh one of the things that I'm
both bullish on and a little bit
terrified of is the direction that
search is going and so we all build
search engines we've got you know our
favorite uh engine that we're building
with but as these Foundation models uh
become more and more prevalent and are
able to understand multiple modalities
and in particular as we give physical
bodies to these models moving around and
interacting in the world uh there's all
of these different modalities whether
it's You Know audio culture sensory
visual uh temporal there's all these
different modalities that the models are
going to be able to tie into and
interact with and we're already seeing
uh you know robots humanoid robots being
developed and having these models put in
them and they're already able to do um
amazing things at least in the lab um
and so I think as we think about what we
do with search I think that search as
the data source that allows these models
to pull in data to perform Rag and uh
enable enables them to get the latest up
toate information uh allows them to get
relevant information um I think that
search is going to morph and change so
that uh it's no longer just like a
system holding data but I think start is
going to become sort of ubiquitous is
the the data layer that powers Ai and
we're already seeing it happen so um
that's it for me um if you want to chat
afterward I'm happy to um otherwise I
will turn it over thanks Charlie thank
you very much
Trey uh judging by that last picture I
had no idea that all my work in search
would lead to a robot that can do the
washing up but I think that's a
fantastic development
that so we've got time for a CP the
questions for Trey okay awesome anyone
in the room has a question for
Trey okay to get you kicked off I'm
going to start with one of our online
questions um so C Freya asks uh how do
you work with the sparity of intera
interaction data in a data
set uh so this is a question about
signals in the context of recommendation
systems when you have very sparse data
to sure sure sure um so um going back to
the um that Spectrum I showed of search
and recommendations um I typically don't
think of recommendations is starting
with the uh Matrix factorization for me
recommendation starts with the very
first piece of context I have about a
user so if let's say I have a job search
engine for example um someone comes to
my website uh before they type in
anything I have an IP address from them
which means I know maybe unless they're
on a VPN roughly where they're located
that's cont text that I can use to
recommend things to them for example if
someone types in nurse uh why in the
world would I um show them nurse jobs in
London if I live in you know New York I
I should show them things that are local
and close to them so that's a sort of
first step towards recommendations is
using a little bit of context to just
sway the results as you collect more and
more interaction data you know maybe
they type a query maybe they type in
multiple queries maybe they click on
things those results can be used to
personalize even with a giant Matrix
factorization so yeah when you get to
the Matrix factorization um and generate
the recommendations using you know an
algorithm that you know is able to deal
with enough data um you get good
recommendations but for for me it's a
spectrum of content-based matching all
the way up to entirely behavioral-based
matching and um for me the the goal is
whatever context you do have available
you use that and the more the better but
if you've got limited context you just
use the limited context thank you thank
you do we have a question for the
oh you're all very shy this morning
we'll get we'll get you going later
don't worry okay so uh another very
quick question from uh Jack uh do you
usually train a single LTR model both
for searches and query list
recommendations have you seen this work
well for cross learning between the two
use cases Sor I say the last word again
have you seen this work well for cross
learning between the two use cases same
LTR model for both searches and
recommendations
um uh
so typically the I drive recommendations
if it's user-based recommendations I
typically drive them based upon the
behavioral data um whether it's the
Matrix factorization or you know
behavioral embeddings that we've taken
from documents um based upon
interactions with do those documents
from other users um ltrr um I think of
as a
generalizable uh ranking classifier um
typically uh so you can take the
behavioral data and uh train your LTR
model with the behavioral data um I
typically treat them as sort of separate
layers of the stack and layer them on
top of each other so I typically create
an LTR model that's more content based
um and then have the personalization
model be more vector-based and sort of
um apply them on top of each other um
you definitely can use the behavioral
data in the LTR model um but I typically
have not taken that approach so yeah
thank you all right I think we're going
to leave it there thank you very much
Tre grer thank you